<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Each biome has its own food web. Constructing a food-web can be quite complex, and so we have a simplified model:<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>In T13 we place an Omnivore at the centre of that Food web. This is the local "Broccen territory". Other Omnivores may be present in the area, but the largest Omnivore represents the territory and is called the Key Omnivore.<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Omnivores are often opportunistic changing diet throughout the year, eating whatever is bountiful at that time.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Omnivores require an edible plant in each season (although winter is often an exception) and at least one other animal (often insects) that they eat.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>The more plants and animals that are available the larger the Omnivore path can be. In a completely blank biome we begin at 2 Pips equivalent. In a more normal biome we begin at 6. </li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Next we add some Herbivores. These Green Field paths link particular species of plants across the biome and beyond. The Bulmäs that follow the green paths call themselves the Fields of the Goddess, although the exact name of that goddess varies by Field.<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Individual Herbivore species typically specialise in eating a single plant, or a certain type of leaf, seed or fruit of a certain plant. </li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Larger and more densely growing plants support larger animals and larger populations of smaller animals. The largest herbivores require huge amounts of food, eating leaves and in some cases whole plants.  </li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>In a normal biome we assume that for each Plant species there are at least 4 species of Herbivore that are exploiting some part of that plant. The smallest of these will be 2 Pips (and include the gut bacteria of larger Herbivores), the largest 5 Pips, usually. </li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>The very largest Herbivore in a biome will typically have 1 or 2 Pips Pips more than the key Omnivore. Although near the Labyrinth this can change, with many larger Herbivore paths being dead.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Predators are added next. The red paths follow the green, but also jump between them. The Predatory Bulmäs call themselves Hunters, and follow the teachings of the Horned Consort, who goes by many names.<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Predators specialisation is slightly different to herbivores. <!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Parasite Predators often specialise in a single species of Herbivore. They adapt to live their whole life cycle inside one herbivore and often another predator.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Ambush Predators generally wait for prey to come along. Ambush predators typically do not specialise in hunting a particular prey, they just kill what comes by, at least, as long as it is small enough to kill and big enough (or there are enough of them) to be worth eating.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Pursuit Predators generally see their prey and run at it. They often specialise in specific prey animals, but may be more generally attracted to motion, although usually it is motion of a certain sized animal that attracts them. Animals larger or significantly smaller than the preferred prey size will be ignored.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Stalking Predators use superior senses to search for prey animals and then choose whether to ambush or pursue.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Snaring Predators build webs, snares and traps to capture prey animals, that they often then later dispatch and kill. Spiders appear to be the original snaring predators, although humans have taken the crown.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Pack Predators work together using group tactics and communication skills. This allows them to hunt much larger prey more successfully, often out-competing larger predators.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Predators rarely make it to the same size as the Omnivore in their food web, but many are much bigger than their prey.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Detritivores and decomposers eat whatever is left. They are Vermis, although some are more Lord Vermis than others.<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Detritivores eat dead plants and long dead meat. They are the rotting process itself in many ways. Specialization usually relates to the animal type that they started as:<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Predators that shift into Detritivore niches are usually called scavengers. They typically evolve ways to exploit animal parts others cannot, such as bones. </li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Herbivores that shift into Detritivore niches are sometimes known as decomposers, although this technically only refers to the smaller bacteria, bottom-feeder is also appropriate in an aquatic niche. Herbivores that eat dead wood are called sapro-xylophagous, etc.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Omnivores that shift into Detritivore niches often assume Scavenger status, although sometimes they adopt exceptionally specific niches.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Most Detritivores and decomposers are very small, scavengers tend to be as big as the Predators in the area, they are sometimes also the key Omnivore at the same time.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list --></li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>Food webs at the edges of biomes typically interact. Often with at least one animal living in both biomes. Typically adjacent biomes will have a different Omnivore at the centre of their food webs. The size of the Omnivore depends on the abundance of available water and nutrition in the biome.</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list -->